<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
<!ENTITY zwsp "&#8203;">
<!ENTITY nbhy "&#8209;">
<!ENTITY wj "&#8288;">
]>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="info" docName="draft-many-tiptop-ip-architecture-00" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" version="3">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IP in Deep Space">An Architecture for IP in Deep Space</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-many-tiptop-ip-architecture-00"/>
    <author fullname="Marc Blanchet" initials="MB">
      <organization>Viagenie</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>marc.blanchet@viagenie.ca</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Wesley Eddy" initials="WE">
      <organization>MTI Systems</organization>
      <address>
          <postal>
            <country>USA</country>
          </postal>
        <email>wes@mti-systems.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Tony Li" initials="TL">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
      <address>
          <postal>
            <country>USA</country>
          </postal>
        <email>tony.li@tony.li</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <keyword>dtn</keyword>
    <keyword>quic</keyword>
    <keyword>space</keyword>
    <keyword>deep space</keyword>
    <keyword>ip</keyword>
    <keyword>dns</keyword>
    <keyword>routing</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
	Deep space communications involve long delays (e.g., Earth to
	Mars is 4-20 minutes) and intermittent communications, because
	of orbital dynamics. The IP protocol stack used on the Internet is
	based on assumptions of shorter delays and mostly uninterrupted
	communications. This document describes the architecture of the
	IP protocol stack tailored for its use in deep space. It
	involves buffering IP packets in IP forwarders facing
	intermittent links, signaling buffer storage near capacity,
	and adjusting transport protocol configuration and application
	protocol timers. This architecture applies to the Moon, Mars, or
	general interplanetary networking.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
	Deep space communications involve long delays (e.g., Earth to
	Mars is 4-20 minutes) and intermittent communications, because
	of orbital dynamics. Up to now, communications have been done on
	a layer-2 point-to-point basis, with sometimes the use of
	relays, but no layer-3 networking has been in use. <xref
	target="RFC4838"/> reports an assessment done around 25 years
	ago concluding that the IP protocol stack was not suitable for
	deep space networking. This result led to the definition of a
	completely new protocol stack based on a store-and-forward
	paradigm implemented in the Bundle Protocol(BP) <xref
	target="RFC9171"/> and its various components, such as
	convergence-layer adapters (<xref target="RFC9174"/>, <xref
	target="RFC7122"/>) and BP Security (BPSEC) <xref
	target="RFC9172"/>.
      </t>
      <t>More recently, space agencies plan to deploy IP
      networks on celestial bodies, such as the Moon <xref
      target="ioag"/> or Mars<xref target="ioag-mars"/>, on the
      surface and in orbital vicinity, using layer 2 technologies such
      as Wi-Fi or 5G. On the surface, the plan is to have a dense
      network around facilities and habitats.</t>
      <t>Mission concepts are also based on a cluster of multiple network nodes nearby at Lagrange points.</t>
      <t>
	A previous document <xref
	target="I-D.many-deepspace-ip-assessment"/> revisited the
	initial assessment of not using IP and concluded that the IP
	stack is viable in deep space, given the IP stack evolution
	that happened since the original evaluation. This document
	defines an architecture to use IP in deep space networking. IP
	in deep space means running IP over deep space layer-2 links,
	a reliable transport over IP, applications protocols over that
	transport, and applying proper routing, security, and network
	management on that IP network. Reusing the whole IP stack in
	deep space enables the reuse of all protocols, tools, and
	software currently used on the Internet. However, as one might
	already argue, many components of the IP stack cannot be used
	as is and therefore requires careful configuration and
	deployment considerations that are discussed in this document.
      </t>
      <t>
	Delay-Tolerant Networking (DTN), also known as Delay and
	Disruption-Tolerant Networking, has been used to identify the
	problem space, and since the solution was based on the Bundle
	protocol, DTN has also been associated with the Bundle
	protocol. This document tries to solve the DTN problem using
	the Internet Protocol stack. Therefore, in this document, the
	DTN keyword is used to name the problem space, not the Bundle
	protocol solution.
      </t>
      <t>
	Since the Moon is a few light seconds away from Earth, it is
	possible to configure and run various IP-based protocols and
	applications to make it "work". Mars with a much longer delay
	is more difficult. Therefore, this document uses Mars as the
	base example, knowing that if it works for Mars, a much harder
	problem, it could be replicated easily for the Moon or other
	networks made with relays around a celestial body. This
	framework would also work for longer delays, such as reaching
	Jupiter or the whole Solar System Internet (SSI), but it is
	not specifically discussed. This document uses "deep space"
	extensively as opposed to "space" which often includes
	earth-orbiting communications, which are not covered this
	document. Even if the definition of deep space per the ITU
	does not include the Moon, this document applies to IP
	networks on the Moon.
      </t>
      <t>It should also be noted that DTN and BP were also designed
      for non-space use cases. While this document focuses on the deep
      space use case, it shall work for the other use cases of BP, but
      these use cases are outside of the scope of this document.</t>
      <t>Space missions are typically planned for many years and are
      long-lived, spanning years or even decades. Spacecraft are
      controlled from Earth and therefore should always be manageable
      from Earth. Given the remoteness and the difficulty of physically accessing the spacecraft software upgrades and configuration changes are avoided whenever possible.</t>
      <t>As with the Bundle protocol, this framework proposes to use
      IP in deep space with a similar store-and-forward
      paradigm. Therefore, the IP layer has to deal with the fact that
      a destination may not be currently reachable and that IP packets
      could be stored for an unusual amount of time, such as minutes,
      hours, or days, in the forwarding device waiting for a new
      link-up  opportunity. The transport layer should be able to work
      with long and variable delays, including intermittent
      communications. The application protocols and the applications
      themselves should be properly set to wait a longer time than on
      the current Internet to receive a response to a query. Finally, all network services such as routing, security, naming, and network management should also be adapted to this new context. This document is structured around these layers.</t>
      <section>
        <name>Document and Discussion Location</name>
        <t>The source of this document is located at https://github.com/marcblanchet/draft-deepspace-ip-architecture. Comments or changes are welcomed using a PR or an issue.</t>
        <t>This subject should be discussed on the deepspace@ietf.org mailing list.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="usecases">
      <name>Use Cases</name>
      <t>Multiple countries are developing systems for a sustained
      lunar presence combining manned and robotic missions, within
      several years.  IP has been included in the stack for the
      International Deep Space Interoperability Standards <xref
      target="idsis"/>, and the LunaNet Interoperability Specification
      <xref target="lnis"/>.  There is a general intention to extend
      and reuse systems developed for lunar use for later use on Mars.
      </t>
      <t>Separate space agencies and private companies are deploying
      lunar space stations, orbiters, landers, rovers, habitats,
      crewed mission elements, and other assets.  Due to the pervasive use and support of IP in modern computing systems, it is naturally used onboard many space systems, and between co-located systems. As more-and-more IP-enabled assets become deployed in lunar vicinity, they will increasingly create opportunities to interconnect them.  In fact, internetworking of lunar (and future Mars) systems is becoming essential, as plans call explicitly for cooperation between mission elements and communications/navigation system assets operated by different space agencies and/or private companies acting as service providers.  There are expected to be several different lunar network service providers (LNSPs) offering different varieties of relayed and/or direct services.  It may be expected that lunar IP networks should over time become united into larger aggregates, and even into a single interoperable network (as intended within the LunaNet conception).</t>
      <t>Routing within and between dynamically connected network elements may be handled in various ways, as the practices develop and specific systems are deployed.  There will likely be coordination between LNSPs and some methods to share and control pre-determined time-varying static routes (similar to PCE architecture), traffic volume expectations, security policies, etc.  The early steps in lunar networking may not actually interconnect the global Internet directly with the lunar surface, though later on this may become reasonable.</t>
      <section anchor="examplenetwork">
        <name>Examplary Network</name>
        <t>The examplary network for this document is where deep space links are using IP over CCSDS space links<xref target="IPoverCCSDSSpaceLinks"/> and that on and around a celestial body, a connected IP network is established with local network infrastructure and services. Orbiters around the celestial body provides connectivity to and from Earth to the devices on the celestial body. As an example, a rover on the Mars surface is connected to a Mars surface IP network which receives intermittent connectivity from a few orbiters with an average of 6 hours per orbit. Some of those orbiters have circular orbits, other elleptical. The latter means that the overpass are not at a fixed frequency. The orbiters are connected to Earth ground station while they are in line of sight with Earth. Earth and Mars have variable distance from 4 to 20 minutes light seconds. That one way delay however change "slowly" as the planets are orbiting around the Sun.</t>
        <t>When an orbiter has direct line of sight with Earth, it can receive from and transmit packets to Earth. During that window, it may have connectivity using another radio or laser to devices on the orbit or on the surface, but very often it does not. Therefore, during those periods where only one segment of the path is up, the orbiter must buffer the received packets until the next segment becomes available when it forwards the packets and flushes the buffer.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="marscurrent">
        <name>Current situation on Mars</name>
        <t>While the target scenarios for Moon or Mars are way more complex than what is deployed today, it is useful to know what has been deployed already. This section describes the Mars communications infrastructure as it relates to its layer 2</t>
        <t>On Mars, there are a few devices such as rovers or helicopters that are in use. There are currently 5 active orbiters that provide communications relay services between Mars surface and Earth. On Earth, various antennas such as the Deep Space Network(DSN)<xref target="DSN"/> are used for communicating with Mars. The MAROS project at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory is a broker software enabling missions to enter data about the communications capabilities such as frequencies, bandwidth, window of communication time, ... so that rover missions can schedule the available communications windows for transmitting and receiving. Most orbiters are used and scheduled in MAROS. One of the Mars orbiters is Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter(MRO)<xref target="mro"/>. It was launched in 2005 and has a single 40Mhz processor but over 100G of solid state memory. As demonstrated by a study<xref target="marscommstudy"/> on Mars communication windows, the communication windows seem of having a constant frequency, but the reality shows that they are pretty variable, which means a very large range of resulting round-trip time (RTT) for communications from Earth to Mars and back. For example, within 3 months in 2024, the RTT varied from 30 minutes to 170 hours.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="layer2">
      <name>Layer 2 in Deep Space</name>
      <section anchor="layer2surface">
        <name>Celestial Body Surface</name>
        <t>The Interagency Operations Advisory Group(IOAG)<xref target="ioag"/> has defined the communications architecture for Moon and Mars. On the celestial body surface, it is planned to use 3GPP and IEEE 802.* link layer protocols. The IP protocol suite is expected to be used over these link layers.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="layer2ccsds">
        <name>Deep Space Links</name>
        <t>Deep space links typically use the Consultative Committee for Space Data Standards(CCSDS)<xref target="CCSDSWEB"/> standards for link layers, such as Telecommand(TC)<xref target="CCSDS_TC"/>, Telemetry (TM)<xref target="CCSDS_TM"/>, Advanced Orbiting Systems(AOS)<xref target="CCSDS_AOS"/>, Proximity1(Prox1)<xref target="CCSDS_PROX1"/>or the Unified Space Data Link Protocol (USLP)<xref target="CCSDS_USLP"/>. CCSDS has defined a generic encapsulation mechanism for the payloads for all these link layer protocols which defines IP as an encapulated protocol<xref target="IPoverCCSDSSpaceLinks"/><xref target="SANAIPEHeaderRegistry"/>. Therefore, IP packets can be transported over any CCSDS link layers.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="layer2orbit">
        <name>Celestial Body Orbits</name>
        <t>On celestial body orbits, IOAG has planned the use of CCSDS link layer protocols. However, as on Earth, it may be possible to use 6G-NTN technology around celestial bodies, such as Moon or Mars orbits. 6G-NTN technologies use IP as its layer3 technology.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="ip">
      <name>Internet Protocol</name>
      <t>IPv4 or IPv6 packets can be carried as is over long delays and disruptions, as IP itself has no notion of time. Originally, the Time To Live(TTL) field of IPv4 was defined based on time<xref target="STD5"/>, but it has been effectively implemented as an hop count, which was renamed as "Hop Count" in IPv6<xref target="STD86"/>. Nothing needs to be changed to the IP protocol or its packet format.</t>
      <section>
        <name>IP Forwarding and Store-and-Forward</name>
        <t>
	  For deep space applications, an IP packet may need to be
	  stored temporarily over much longer periods than are typical
	  for the Internet when the next hop is currently unreachable
	  or undefined, which can happen due to orbital dynamics. This
	  is commonly referred to as "store-and-forward" and bears no
	  relationship to the same term when used in reference to
	  switch architectures.
	</t>
        <t>
	  This store and forward mechanism may be implemented at layer
	  2 as is currently done by the Mars orbiters. In this case,
	  the frames are stored, independent of payload type.  In this
	  case, IP packets are unaware of the store-and-forward and no
	  changes are needed in the IP forwarding function.  The L2
	  network is just behaving as a point-to-point link with a
	  large and variable latency.
	</t>
        <t>
	  If an IP router has an interfaces on an intermittent link,
	  then a queueing discipline should be used to
	  store packets. This might be implemented as a deep queue with
	  active queue management(AQM)<xref target="RFC7567"/>. When the
	  link to the next hop is up again, maybe minutes or hours
	  later, the stored packets can then be transmitted.
	</t>
        <t>
	  This store-and-forward mechanism requires proper
	  provisioning of storage at each forwarding interface for the
	  target deployment and usage. Mechanisms such as ECN (<xref
	  target="ecn"/>) can be used to signal storage congestion can
	  be used to request that end nodes throttle their
	  transmissions.  If the appropriate queue is full, then the
	  interface MAY drop packets and MAY send ICMP error messages
	  to the source, so that the transport protocol can recover by
	  resending the dropped packets. The choice of which packets
	  to drop during a queue congestion event depends on the
	  queuing policies configured in the node, which may be a
	  function of diffserv/traffic class, source or destination IP
	  addresses, flow label, or other parameters. An example is
	  described in <xref target="I-D.blanchet-tvr-forwarding"/>.
	</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="headercompression">
        <name>Header Compression</name>
        <t>
	  Deep space links are point-to-point links and bandwidth in
	  space is very valuable, so header compression is very
	  useful. Static Context Header Compression (SCHC) <xref
	  target="I-D.ietf-schc-architecture"/> is a header
	  compression technique that relies on rules in a static
	  context, and is therefore more efficient for deep
	  space. SCHC should be considered on a deep space
	  point-to-point link or a string of L2 links.
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>IP Routing</name>
      <t>
	Existing routing protocols have a requirement for proof of
	liveness between protocol partners that is implemented through
	the periodic exchange of packets between partners. This is
	impractical on long-delay or intermittent links, so a PCE
	<xref target="RFC4655"/> based approach seems appropriate for
	those domains possibly supplemented by contact plan schedules
	<xref target="I-D.blanchet-tvr-contactplan"/> <xref
	target="I-D.ietf-tvr-schedule-yang"/>. Interconnection between
	domains can still be done with BGP <xref target="RFC4271"/>,
	but long-delay or intermittent links should be
	avoided. Domains straddling such links will need to provide
	proxy advertisements for prefixes reachable across such links.
      </t>
      <t>
	Optimal routing for domains with intermittent links is out of
	scope for this document.
      </t>
      <t>
	On the surface of celestial bodies and in proximal orbit,
	traditional protocols are applicable and should be used (e.g.,
	<xref target="I-D.li-arch-sat"/>).
      </t>
      <section title="Addressing">
	<t>
	  The IP address space is a hierarchical namespace where
	  ranges of addresses are encoded as "prefixes".  Individual
	  domains advertise a set of prefixes to the broader Internet
	  and assign these addresses internally. Prefixes may be
	  aggregated into less-specific prefixes, which makes the
	  routing subsystem more efficient by decreasing overhead.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Space networks provide a unique opportunity to provide
	  extremely efficient routing by assigning a unique prefix or
	  block of addresses per celestial body and its proximal
	  orbits. Management of the IP address space is currently
	  documented in <xref target="RFC7020"/>, but this only covers
	  continental regions and does not provide for addressing for
	  space.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Address space for outer space should be managed by a single
	  Regional Internet Registry (RIR) and blocks of address space
	  should be allocated for each celestial body of
	  interest. Space service providers should use prefixes
	  assigned by this RIR.
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Transport</name>
      <section anchor="udp">
        <name>UDP</name>
        <t>UDP<xref target="RFC768"/> has no notion of time, therefore can be used as is in deep space. Protocols using UDP transport can therefore be used in space as is, if they do not rely on time or if they can be configured with timeouts appropriate in deep space.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="quic-section">
        <name>QUIC</name>
        <t>QUIC<xref target="RFC9000"/> like most IP transports implements congestion control mechanisms, which, based on various metrics such as calculated delays or packet loss, pace the rate of sending packets at the source node to decrease the perceived congestion in the network. QUIC supports many new features suitable and useful in deep space such as 1 RTT for connection establishment and security, mobility, 0RTT, streams, user-space, ....</t>
        <t>Current implementations of QUIC typically set various transport configuration parameters suitable for the Internet environment, with RTT in the hundreds of milliseconds and relatively always connected network. Therefore, QUIC stacks using default configurations will not work in deep space. However, studies and simulations<xref target="quic-sim"/> showed that with proper transport configuration parameters, QUIC stacks support delays and disruptions in deep space. <xref target="I-D.many-deepspace-quic-profile"/> describes how to properly configure a QUIC stack for deep space application, where the QUIC transport is unaware of disruptions. If the transport is aware of the disruptions, then further optimizations may be done.</t>
        <t>The ability to have multiple streams and applications within a single QUIC connection is valuable and useful for deep space. A ground station may setup the initial QUIC connection with a spacecraft and then carry all needed applications and streams over that same connection for the whole duration of the mission.</t>
        <t>Session key and certificate lifetime together with certificate validation and trust chain anchors need to be carefully configured and handled.</t>
        <t>QUIC proxies<xref target="I-D.ietf-masque-quic-proxy"/> can be used at space edge to isolate, apply policies or to optimize trafic at ingress/egress to a celestial body network.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Other Transports</name>
        <t>Other transports such as TCP<xref target="RFC9293"/>, SCTP<xref target="RFC9260"/>, DCCP<xref target="RFC4340"/> and others were not investigated for their suitability in space.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="ecn">
        <name>Explicit Congestion Notification(ECN)</name>
        <t>Explicit Congestion Notification(ECN)<xref target="RFC3168"/> enables a network forwarder to signal to the sources to pace down in the context of congestion. In deep space where forwarders will be buffering packets, the actual congestion is when the storage is approaching its full capacity. ECN enables the forwarders to signal that issue. Given delays and disruptions which means the reception by the source may take longer time, the forwarders should be pro-active and preempt based on the types of links and actual rate of storage usage. IP clients with QUIC should process the received ECN signals appropriately.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="http-section">
      <name>HTTP</name>
      <t>HTTP by itself has no notion of time. An HTTP request and response may take minutes or hours to be completed. However, current infrastructure and software on Internet have various time-related configurations that will not work as is in the deep space context.</t>
      <t>HTTP headers containing time, such as Cache-Control and Expires <xref target="RFC9111"/>, should not be used or if used be set to large enough values to cover the longest delay so that expiration does not happen before the actual data arrives at the destination. As with any HTTP application and content on Internet, these headers should be set properly based on the deployment use case, which is ever more important for deep space. Similarly, when continuous content transfer is used, as with 100-Continue <xref target="RFC9110"/>, proper values for headers should be set.</t>
      <t>HTTP clients and servers typically have default timeouts that shall be modified. For example, curl <xref target="curl"/> has the "-m" option for this use case. Similarly, HTTP server implementations have various timeouts configuration variables to be set properly. Testing with HTTP client Curl and HTTP server nginx and an introduced network delay of 20 minutes showed that HTTP communications work just fine with very basic configuration changes.</t>
      <t>HTTP applications themselves must be developed using an asynchronous pattern and if they have timeouts, they should be adjusted appropriately.</t>
      <t>Internet Web sites are designed with the assumption of hundred of milliseconds delay and relatively always connected, where pages contain multiple queries to further get resources, media, queries to web services and downloading additional code and frameworks. This could work in theory in this context of space, but it will not be optimal, as multiple queries will be generated and therefore taking multiple RTT before the whole page is received complete. This issue can be mitigated by using various techniques such as Web Assembly <xref target="wasm"/> or pre-caching. Moreover, tt could be possible to have very basic HTML pages with zero or very few href and no media content unless locally cached to be used. An example would be a rover on Mars presenting an HTTP server with a base and bare HTML page to offer basic info on its status (maybe all in text) and some additional detailed pages, most likely also in base html text. However, it is foreseen that most applications based on QUIC-HTTP transport in deep space would be using REST or similar asynchronous patterns and not typical web browsing.</t>
      <t>Caching should be used extensively on celestial bodies networks to maximize local fetching. Preemptive caching by pre-populating caches with data that shall be used locally on the celestial body network shall be done as much as possible to provide better response time on the local celestial body network.</t>
      <t>QPACK <xref target="RFC9204"/> should be considered for higher bandwidth efficiency.</t>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Network services</name>
      <section anchor="dns">
        <name>Naming</name>
        <t>At a small scale, one can use IP addresses directly or can use static names to IP address mappings such as /etc/hosts. However, this does not provide easy dynamic updates, scaling by hierarchy, service discovery, authentication of records, ... Therefore, the Domain Name System (DNS) shall be considered early on in the space deployment. However, naming hierarchy and infrastructure has to be carefully designed to avoid name resolution over deep space links, given that answers may come after minutes or hours. There are clear advantages of having the space name hierarchy anchored to the current Internet root, as it enables DNSSEC using the same security infrastructure currently used and deployed. Using the same root also does not require new policies. A new TLD or a new root is way more complicated and does not bring any significant value compared to using the current domain tree.</t>
        <t>Care must be taken to manage key lifecycles and resource record lifetimes. <xref target="I-D.many-dnsop-dns-isolated-networks"/> discusses the various methods and naming hierarchy that can be used in space.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Network Management</name>
        <t>NETCONF<xref target="RFC6241"/> and RESTCONF<xref target="RFC8040"/> shall be used with proper configuration values to avoid timeouts and appropriate transport. NETCONF over QUIC transport<xref target="I-D.ietf-netconf-over-quic"/> or RESTCONF over HTTP over QUIC transport shall be configured with appropriate QUIC transport parameters as discussed in <xref target="quic-section"/>.</t>
        <t>While being declared historic in IETF, SNMP<xref target="RFC1157"/> runs over UDP and have no notion of time. Therefore, with proper configuration of client timeout, it can be used as is to manage nodes and services in deep space.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>Using the current IP protocol stack in deep space inherit all the work on privacy, cryptography, key management, firewalls and relative high scrutiny of protocols that is deployed on Internet. As an example, TLS has been way more scrutinized than almost any other secure transport protocol. Moreover, given that no changes are made in the protocols, this architecture does not bring new security issues. Obviously, the deep space security requirements are different than on Earth Internet, but nothing has been found to prevent the conformance of the IP protocol stack to those requirements.</t>
      <t>As it is currently planned, the deep space network shall be isolated from the current Internet by "air gap", to disable any direct communications from Internet to deep space. Moreover, destination IP prefixes filtering shall be used to restrict the traffic to only the relevant one for each link. Note that this shall also be implemented in the routing control plane, but additional security might be appropriate to further protect the deep space links.</t>
      <t>Each celestial network edge device shall have firewall rules to disable non-useful trafic to go through deep space links. If communications from Mars may only occur to Earth, but not Moon, then appropriate filtering based on destination IP prefixes shall be used. Given the air gap on Earth for Internet, there shall be no default route advertised in space that could for example point to Earth Internet.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
          <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.768.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.1157.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3168.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4340.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4655.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4838.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.6241.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7020.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7122.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7567.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8040.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9000.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9110.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9111.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9171.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9172.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9204.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9260.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9293.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml9/reference.STD.0005.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml9/reference.STD.0086.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.blanchet-tvr-contactplan.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.blanchet-tvr-forwarding.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-masque-quic-proxy.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-netconf-over-quic.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-schc-architecture.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-tvr-schedule-yang.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.li-arch-sat.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.many-deepspace-ip-assessment.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.many-deepspace-quic-profile.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.many-dnsop-dns-isolated-networks.xml"/>
        <reference anchor="IPoverCCSDSSpaceLinks" target="https://public.ccsds.org/Pubs/702x1b1c2.pdf"><front><title>IP OVER CCSDS SPACE LINKS, Blue Book 702</title><author><organization>Consultative Committee on Space Data Systems(CCSDS)</organization></author><date year="2012" month="September"/></front></reference>
        <reference anchor="SANAIPEHeaderRegistry" target="https://sanaregistry.org/r/ipe_header/"><front><title>Internet Protocol Extension Header</title><author/></front></reference>
        <reference anchor="CCSDS_AOS" target="https://public.ccsds.org/Pubs/732x0b4.pdf"><front><title>AOS Space Data Link Protocol, Blue Book 732.0-B-4</title><author><organization>Consultative Committee on Space Data Systems(CCSDS)</organization></author><date year="2021" month="October"/></front></reference>
        <reference anchor="CCSDS_TM" target="https://public.ccsds.org/Pubs/132x0b3.pdf"><front><title>TM Space Data Link Protocol, Blue Book 132.0-B-3</title><author><organization>Consultative Committee on Space Data Systems(CCSDS)</organization></author><date year="2021" month="October"/></front></reference>
        <reference anchor="CCSDS_TC" target="https://public.ccsds.org/Pubs/232x0b4e1c1.pdf"><front><title>TC Space Data Link Protocol, Blue Book 232.0-B-4</title><author><organization>Consultative Committee on Space Data Systems(CCSDS)</organization></author><date year="2021" month="October"/></front></reference>
        <reference anchor="CCSDS_PROX1" target="https://public.ccsds.org/Pubs/211x0b6e1.pdf"><front><title>Proximity-1 Space Link Protocol—Data Link Layer, Blue Book 211.0-B-6</title><author><organization>Consultative Committee on Space Data Systems(CCSDS)</organization></author><date year="2020" month="July"/></front></reference>
        <reference anchor="CCSDS_USLP" target="https://public.ccsds.org/Pubs/732x1b2s.pdf"><front><title>Unified Space Data Link Protocol, Blue Book 732.1-B-2</title><author><organization>Consultative Committee on Space Data Systems(CCSDS)</organization></author><date year="2021" month="October"/></front></reference>
        <reference anchor="wasm" target="https://github.com/webassembly/spec"><front><title>WebAssembly Specifications</title><author><organization>World Wide Web Consortium(W3C)</organization></author></front></reference>
        <reference anchor="ioag" target="https://www.ioag.org/Public%20Documents/Lunar%20communications%20architecture%20study%20report%20FINAL%20v1.3.pdf"><front><title>The Future Lunar Communications Architecture, Report of the Interagency Operations Advisory Group</title><author><organization>Lunar Communications Architecture Working Group, Interagency Operations Advisory Group</organization></author><date year="2022" month="January"/></front></reference>
        <reference anchor="ioag-mars" target="https://www.ioag.org/Public%20Documents/MBC%20architecture%20report%20final%20version%20PDF.pdf"><front><title>The Future
                Mars Communications Architecture, Report of the Interagency Operations Advisory Group
                </title><author><organization>Mars and Beyond Communications Architecture Working Group, Interagency Operations Advisory Group</organization></author><date year="2022" month="February"/></front></reference>
        <reference anchor="picoquic-poc" target="https://www.privateoctopus.com/2023/02/07/quic-to-mars.html"><front><title>QUIC to Mars</title><author initials="C." surname="Huitema" fullname="Christian Huitema"/><date year="2023" month="February"/></front></reference>
        <reference anchor="picoquic" target="https://github.com/private-octopus/picoquic"><front><title>picoquic</title><author initials="C." surname="Huitema" fullname="Christian Huitema"/></front></reference>
        <reference anchor="curl" target="https://curl.se"><front><title>Curl</title><author/></front></reference>
        <reference anchor="CCSDSWEB" target="https://ccsds.org"><front><title>Consultative Committee for Space Data Systems</title><author><organization>CCSDS</organization></author></front></reference>
        <reference anchor="mro" target="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/mars-reconnaissance-orbiter/"><front><title>Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter</title><author/></front></reference>
        <reference anchor="DSN" target="https://www.nasa.gov/directorates/somd/space-communications-navigation-program/what-is-the-deep-space-network/"><front><title>Deep Space Network</title><author/></front></reference>
        <reference anchor="quic-sim" target="https://deepspaceip.github.io/meetings/ietf120/ietf120-deepspaceip-simulation-results.pdf"><front><title>Deep Space IP:
            Some simulation results</title><author fullname="Marc Blanchet" initials="M." surname="Blanchet"><organization>Viagenie</organization></author><date month="July" year="2024"/></front></reference>
        <reference anchor="marscommstudy" target="https://deepspaceip.github.io/meetings/ietf121/ietf121-deepspaceip-mars-communications-study.pdf"><front><title>Earth-Mars Communication Windows Usage Study</title><author fullname="Marc Blanchet" initials="M." surname="Blanchet"><organization>Viagenie</organization></author><date month="October" year="2024"/></front></reference>
        <reference anchor="idsis" target="https://internationaldeepspacestandards.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/communication_reva_final_9-2020.pdf"><front><title>International Communication System
            Interoperability Standards (ICSIS)</title><author/><date month="September" year="2020"/></front></reference>
        <reference anchor="lnis" target="https://www.nasa.gov/directorates/somd/space-communications-navigation-program/lunanet-interoperability-specification/"><front><title>LunaNet Interoperability Specification</title><author/><date month="September" year="2022"/></front></reference>

      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>This work started by reassessing the use of the whole IP stack in the context of deep space. Soon, QUIC was identified as the key technology for this endeavour. Christian Huitema was very helpful in not only confirming the ability to use QUIC but also took the time and effort to test and modify its picoquic stack<xref target="picoquic"/> to confirm the initial hypothesis<xref target="picoquic-poc"/>. Its involvement and confirmation are the key for the launch of this work. Then, Martin Thompson has been also kind to take time to answer initial questions on QUIC, further confirming the possibility of using QUIC for deep space. Since then, many individuals have provided significant comments and perspectives on this subject.</t>
      <t>This document and its underlying work has been reviewed and discussed by many, who have provided valuable feedback and comments, including disagreements, and made an overall more solid document. These people are, in no specific order: TBD.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
